A Guide to the Ellen Wayles Randolph Coolidge Correspondence 1810-1861
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Ellen Wayles Randolph Coolidge Correspondence 1810-1861
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
9090, 9090-c, 38-584
253 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Purchase and gift: 1930 November 5; 1969 June 24; 1981 April 1981
Scope and Content
The collection consists chiefly of correspondence between Ellen Wayles Randolph Coolidge and her mother Martha Jefferson Randolph, and sisters Virginia Trist, Cornelia Randolph and Mary Randolph.
They discuss family and friends; trips to Richmond, Philadelphia and Baltimore; life in Boston, and at Monticello and Poplar Forest; the University of Virginia students, faculty and Board of Visitors; Thomas Jefferson's illness and death, debts, the proposed lottery, and the sale of Monticello and his slaves.
Also Martha Randolph's life in Washington and continuing financial problems; the careers of Joseph Coolidge in the China trade, Nicholas Trist in the diplomatic service, Benjamin Franklin Randolph in medicine and George Wythe Randolph in the navy; and the publication of "Memoirs, correspondence and private papers of Thomas Jefferson."
Other topics of interest include Richmond dentistry, 1819; the panic of 1819 and financial ruin of Wilson Cary Nicholas; Thomas Mann Randolph's strained relations with his family; Lafayette's visit to Monticello; the sale of Jefferson's paintings; Harvard College politics; historian Jared Sparks; Nat Turner's rebellion; the Hemings family, Ellen's maid Sally Cottrell Cole; and contrasts between slaves in the South and domestic servants in New England.
The collection also contains autobiographical reflections by Ellen Coolidge and a volume of copies of correspondence between Ellen Coolidge and Henry Stephens Randall concerning Jefferson and his family.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged chronologically
Contents List
- Thomas Mann Randolph to Joseph C. Cabell 1810 March 23 (Box 1)
  thanks Cabell for his willingness to be a candidate for the Senate when family obligations made it difficult for Randolph to run
- Ellen Wayles Randolph to Martha Randolph [1814] March 2 (Box 1)
  writes concerning clothes making for the family
- Ellen Randolph to Martha Randloph [1814] March 30 (Box 1)
  refers to the sickness of her brother James Randolph and her grandfather Thomas Jefferson, describes a large party at the home of Mrs. [Hastings] Marks ([Anna Scott Jefferson?]) during her visit to Richmond and her impressions of a Mr. Barksdale
- Ellen Randolph to Martha Randolph 1814 April 24 (Box 1)
  describes her social life during her visit to Richmond
- Ellen Randolph to Martha Randolph 1816 January 5 (Box 1)
  describes her journey to Richmond with Jane Hollins Nicholas Randolph to visit her Aunt [Mary] Randolph and Cousin Ann, the unexpected use of General John Hartwell Cocke's carriage on the journey, the comfort rendered by her grandfather's fur, and Jane's stopover at the Governor's Mansion to see her father, Wilson Cary Nicholas
- Ellen Randolph to Martha Randolph 1816 January 22 (Box 1)
  describes her journey from Richmond to Washington to visit the Madisons at the White House
- Ellen Randolph to Martha Randolph 1816 January 31 (Box 1)
  furnishes more details concerning her previous unsatisfactory visit to Richmond and her misadventures in trying to assemble a wardrobe appropriate for society in Washington, she also mentions the illness of Mrs. Madison
- Ellen Randolph to Martha Randolph [1816] February 7 (Box 1)
  provides additional details of her social life while in Washington and sends a packet of letters to Thomas Jefferson
- Ellen Randolph to Martha Randolph [1816] February 17 (Box 1)
  refers to her enjoyment of the Philadelphia circle of visitors, several suitors, her enjoyable stay with the Madisons, especially their gay parties, her visit to the House of Representatives which at times she found both amusing and fatiguing, a Marshall Grouchy with a letter of introduction to Jefferson from the Marquis de Lafayette, her meeting other members of Congress, especially John Forsyth (1780-1841) of Georgia, the painter John Vanderlyn (1775-1852) and Mann Randolph's application for a commission in the Navy promised by the Secretary of the Navy, Benjamin Williams Crowninshield
- Ellen Randolph to Virginia Randolph [1816] February 28 (Box 1)
  refers to the former beauty of the Capitol building before its destruction by the British during the War of 1812 which was evident during her visit to its damp vaults
- Ellen Randolph to Martha Randolph [1816] March 9 (Box 1)
  describes her companions and friends in Washington, the ill health of Mrs. [Stephen?] Decatur, and her desire to visit Baltimore
- Ellen Randolph to Martha Randolph [ante 1816 March 26] (Box 1)
  assures her mother that she will secure the bank notes requested by her father Thomas Mann Randolph as quickly as possible from the Bank of Columbia and that her grandfather should receive them by mail around the first of April; she also mentions her lack of success in finding a book of instruction on the guitar and her purchase of Scientific Dialogues by [Jeremiah Joyce?] (1763-1816)
- Ellen Randolph to Thomas Mann Randolph 1816 March 26 (Box 1)
  informs her father that she has sent the Columbia Bank notes to her grandfather for him and mentions his financial difficulties
- Ellen Randolph to Martha Randolph [ca. 1816 March] (Box 1)
  In these four letters, Ellen talks about her initial disappointment with society in Washington and its trivial conversations, her regret at her prejudice against the Jewish religion practiced by Mr. Gratz, and her visit with the Bayard girls, Sally and Elizabeth; mentions her thankfulness that the most urgent debts of her father are paid, and the sale of Varina; asks permission to travel to Baltimore if the opportunity arises; expresses her uneasiness that the packages of bank notes have yet arrived in the mail and describes the procedure in which she made up the packages, the opportunity to visit Philadelphia, "the real capital of the country" where she proposes to stay with Mrs. Bache, her reception of additional funds from her grandfather's sale of tobacco, her worries over the cost of her travels to her father and grandfather, and Mrs. Madison's suggestion that Martha mail Ellen's letters to her in care of the President so that she might forward them to Philadelphia
- Ellen Randolph to Martha Randolph [1816] April 6 (Box 1)
  writes of her hospitable reception by the Baches of Philadelphia and the ball given upon the night of her arrival
- Ellen Randolph to Martha Randolph [1816 April] (Box 1)
  These two letters mention that Mr. Bache is the brother of Dr. [William?] Bache so well known by her mother, a serenade in which "Jefferson's March" was played, her visit to the house where her mother lived with Mrs. [Thomas] Hopkinson while the family was in Philadelphia, and the lodgings of Jefferson as Secretary of State, and Vice President; She also mentions a visit to the vessel Franklin with Captain Dallas
- Ellen Randolph to Martha Randolph [1816] May 1 (Box 1)
  expresses her preference for Philadelphia over Baltimore and her desire to return home as soon as an escort can be found
- Ellen Randolph to Martha Randolph 1816 May 12 (Box 1)
  mentions her refusal of Mrs. Madison's offer to accompany her to Orange County, Virginia, and Mrs. Burwell's offer to accompany them to Albemarle because both involved delay
- Ellen Randolph to Martha Randolph [1816?] September 27 (Box 1)
  describes the visits of curious and inopportune "sightseers" to Monticello who wanted to catch a glimpse of Thomas Jefferson, while her mother was away at Poplar Forest; provides news of the family routine and of the slaves, and says "give my love to Grandpapa, I have not forgotten to wind up his clocks, and will take good care of his wines, when they arrive"
- Ellen Randolph to Martha Randolph [1816 November?] (Box 1)
  writes of past visitors to [Poplar Forest], the possible visit of Marshall Grouchy and Mr. Lee, Consul at Bourdeaux, during the winter at Monticello, news of the slaves, and that Mr. [Godefroi?] was so taken with Natural Bridge that he wished to purchase it
- Ellen Randolph to Martha Randolph [1816?] December 30 (Box 1)
  describes her visit with Ogle and Catharine Tayloe and mentions a party attended by the New York Senator [Martin] Van Buren, characterized as a "speculation, were he not a widower encumbered with five children"
- Ellen Randolph to Martha Randolph [1817] August 18 (Box 1)
  writes of her trip to Natural Bridge, Virginia, "For me it was a complete chapter of accidents," but worth suffering "for the wonder and delight... at the sight of ... the most sublime of Nature's works"; she also comments on the differences in manners and characteristics of the locals, and her disappointment in the service of Maria
- Ellen Randolph to Martha Randolph [1817] September (Box 1)
  gives her impression of a visitor, Mr. Clay, who was "much more uncivilized than any Indian and wild Hottentots" and mentions the distress of Thomas Jefferson over the death of Mr. Du Pont [de Nemours]
- Ellen Randolph to Martha Randolph 1818 January 28 (Box 1)
  contrasts her life in the cities she visits with that at Monticello, "At Monticello I live in the almost constant exercise of my heart and understanding - having constantly before me objects of the warmest affection and highest admiration - the conversation there is completely the [heart] of reason and I would not permanently change my situation with anyone living ... I bless God for having been born at Monticello, your daughter and so much the object of my dear Grandfather's care," and she also describes merchandise being shipped to Monticello
- Ellen Randolph to Martha Randolph 1818 April 14 (Box 1)
  describes her journey with her grandfather to Poplar Forest, reading while waiting at the taverns, her stay at the Hunter's Inn, Campbell County, and her gossip with acquaintances
- Ellen Randolph to Martha Randolph 1818 September 27 (Box 1)
  describes her visit to Carysbrook, Fluvanna County, remarks that the two Cary families are again on visiting terms, and mentions some music that she is copying for her mother
- Ellen Randolph to Martha Randolph [1818] December 29 (Box 1)
  mentions family news concerning the Cary family
- Ellen Randolph to Martha Randolph [1819] March 18 (Box 1)
  stays in Richmond where her sister Virginia will be able to see a dentist and have her teeth filled, and enumerates the items Virginia should bring with her
- Ellen Randolph to Martha Randolph [1819] March 29 (Box 1)
  describes her Aunt [Harriet Randolph] Hackley's school for girls in Richmond, her Aunt Randolph's intention of selling her furniture and moving to Albemarle, and remarks that "the distress for money is almost universal" indicating the Panic of 1819
- Ellen Randolph to Martha Randolph 1819 April 9 (Box 1)
  mentions her family's financial difficulties and her social activities
- Ellen Randolph to Martha Randolph 1819 April 25 (Box 1)
  describes social life in Richmond with her sister Virginia and Cousin Harriet Randolph and describes Virginia's dental work and her own difficult extraction
- Ellen Randolph to Martha Randolph [1819] July 18 (Box 1)
  describes the hailstorm damage to the windows at Poplar Forest and other damage to the building while unoccupied, reminiscences about previous visits to Poplar Forest and her profitable times of study there in Latin and history, regrets that she is a woman and thus unable to spend her life in pursuit of knowledge, and mentions Thomas Jefferson's visit to Mr. Clay
- Ellen Randolph to Martha Randolph 1819 July 28 (Box 1)
  reveals that "Grandpapa and myself are in the habit of sitting, some time after dinner, in conversation, upon different subjects" while at Poplar Forest, particularly that of the influence of the mother upon the education of the children, the great concern of Thomas Jefferson, Cornelia, and Ellen over the serious illness of their servant Burwell Hemings, a glazier, while at Poplar Forest, John Hemmings careful nursing of Burwell, and the progress Israel has made as a waiter
- Ellen Randolph to Virginia Randolph 1819 August 4 (Box 1)
  mentions the unusually high temperatures experienced at Poplar Forest, a vist to Dr. [Thomas?] Walker's brother's home, meeting the family of one of Jefferson's political enemies, Mr. Watts, and another of Burwell's attacks of illness
- Ellen Randolph to Martha Randolph 1819 August 11 (Box 1)
  discusses the financial ruin of Colonel [Wilson Cary] Nicholas whose estate was placed in the hands of trustees to be sold for payment of his debts, Thomas Jefferson's severe attack of rheumatism, the need for rain, and her pleasure at reading Virgil's Aeneid in the original Latin
- Ellen Randolph to Martha Randolph 1819 August 24 (Box 1)
  voices her concern about the effect of the financial failure of Colonel Wilson Cary Nicholas upon her grandfather's affairs, as well as the emotional impact of possible ruin, and her surprise that Thomas Jefferson had endorsed the notes of Nicholas and also describes their dining habits at Poplar Forest
- Ellen Randolph to Virginia Randolph [1819] August 31 (Box 1)
  regrets the death of Burwell's wife, [Griffy?] and his grief over her death, and expresses her concern for the future of their children
- Ellen Randolph to Virginia Randolph 1820 January 9 (Box 1)
  complains about the disagreeable schedule at Wilmington, Virginia, her trouble with toothache and her use of the tobacco plant to alleviate the pain, and the isolation experienced in Fluvanna County
- Ellen Randolph to Martha Randolph 1820 May 18 (Box 1)
  writes from Richmond at the home of her Aunt Hackley, mentions th musical ability of Mr. Nicholas of Philadelphia, and her dislike of learning to play waltzes
- Ellen Randolph to Martha Randolph 1820 May 31 (Box 1)
  mentions the affection and regard of her family and friends in Richmond, a period of depression and lassitude, and her disappointment over Mr. Nicholas' refusal to sing
- Ellen Randolph to Martha Randolph 1820 September 13 (Box 1)
  while at Poplar Forest she recounts her disagreeable sojourn at [Noah] Flood's Tavern, Buckingham County, where they stayed because of the heavy rain on the journey, her grandfather's trouble with swelling of his legs, and finding the harpsichord in poor condition and the books moldy
- Ellen Randolph to Marth Randolph 1821 November 19 (Box 1)
  describes her travel to Washington with Nicholas [Trist?] and their stop-over at Fredericksburg
- Ellen Randolph to Martha Randolph 1821 December 14 (Box 1)
  mentions the sickness of her Aunt Randolph in Washington, an ardent admirer William Taylor of Norfolk, a Colonel Freeman who credits Thomas Jefferson with his promotion, and her social prospects
- Ellen Randolph to Martha Randolph 1822 April 3 (Box 1)
  stresses her need for financial support in order to visit Baltimore, asks her father to press President Monroe to pay money due him, remarks upon her father's strange temper, and regrets her own thriftless temperament
- Joseph Coolidge, Jr. to Martha Randolph 1825 May 9 (Box 1)
  writes concerning Ellen's illness and gives her the advice of his own physician, Dr. Spooner
- Joseph Coolidge, Jr. to Martha Randolph 1825 June 25 (Box 1)
  describes Ellen and his honeymoon trip, to Fredericksburg and on their way home to Boston
- Ellen Wayles (Randolph) Coolidge to Martha Randolph 1825 June 26 (Box 1)
  describes the society they enjoyed while waiting for their luggage to arrive, and discusses the disposition of the slave Sally [Cole] saying, "if she chooses to be sold let her choose her own master, if to be hired she should have the same liberty, or at least not be sent anywhere she is unwilling to go."
- Virginia (Randolph) Trist to Ellen Coolidge 1825 June 27 (Box 1)
  mentions the sense of loss the family has experienced at Ellen's absence from their society at Monticello, especially felt by Thomas Jefferson, and speaks of her own love for her absent sister
- Ellen Coolidge to Martha Randolph [1825] July 9 (Box 1)
  mentions seeing the ascent of a balloon at Castle Garden and seeing the Marquis [de Lafayette] who promised to be at Monticello by the end of July or August
- Cornelia Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1825 July 13 (Box 1)
  mentions Thomas Jefferson's poor health, refers to the family's impending financial misfortunes, shares the gossip about the University of Virginia, including finding Mr. Raphael's sister in the dormitories at midnight, the "war" between the girls of Charlottesville and the students at the University, the girls boycott of one of the University barbecues, the equine exploits of her escort Mr. Charles Bonnycastle, and the birth of a daughter to Mr. and Mrs. Thomas Key
- Ellen Coolidge to Martha Randolph 1825 July 31 (Box 1)
  Ellen describes her arrival in Boston and her reception from the Coolidges, and begrudges the selfishness of the family of T. Eston and Jane Cary Randolph at Ashton who took her mother away from attending her father at Monticello
- Joseph Coolidge to Martha Randolph [1825 July?] (Box 1)
  writes from Baltimore on his honeymoon trip to Boston describing their itinerary
- Ellen Coolidge to Martha Randolph [ca. 1825 August] (Box 1)
  shares her difficulty in adjusting to the peculiar customs and prejudices of her new countrymen in Boston, her abhorrence of the New England diet staples of fish, pudding, and pork, the lack of interest in books and literature or nonconventional ideas
- Joseph Coolidge, Jr. to Martha Randolph 1825 August (Box 1)
  describes their trip to Boston, Ellen's reaction to travel and her reception among his friends, his thankfulness at Thomas Jefferson's improving health, and says about Jefferson "public opinion in this section of our country has changed, of late, much, very much, in regard to him: public and private testimony to his patriotism, and character are no longer infrequent; to his literary merits they have never been."
- Martha Randolph 1825 August 2 (Box 1)
  discusses the disposition of the slave Susan, Ellen's impression of Saratoga Springs, the injunction Mr. Randolph secured to prevent the public sale of his property set for the 8th and to allow Francis Gilmer to sell the estate at private sales, her dread of the sale of the slaves, "the Negroes may be disposed of to people that we know, in many instances friend, and neighbor; my Father no doubt being allowed time can also assist in the purchase. My mind is greatly relieved by this arrangement. The discomfort of slavery I have borne all my life, but its sorrows in all their bitterness I had never before conceived. The sale of Susan was only a prelude in my imagination to the scenes which the 8th would exhibit in all their horrors, for the country is overrun with those trafficers in human blood the Negro buyer, and that advertisement would have been the signal to have collected them from every part of the state."
- Cornelia Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1825 August 3 (Box 1)
  writes concerning the considerable number of visitors at Monticello due to the popular convention in Staunton to discuss the need for a state constitutional convention which helped to pave the way for the Constitutional Convention of 1829-1830, Dr. Dunglison's care of Thomas Jefferson as his physician, their dislike of the George Blaettermanns, the new faculty including Robley Dunglison, Charles Bonnycastle, Thomas Key, John Patton Emmet, and George Tucker, the hope of Jefferson that Judge Dade will accept the law professorship, and the consideration of Francis Gilmer for that position
- Mary Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1825 August 18 (Box 1)
  writes of the Marquis de Lafayette's impending visit, the disruption it will cause and its effect upon Thomas Jefferson's health and comfort, family news, and Maria Carr's serious illness
- Cornelia Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1825 August 26 (Box 1)
  writes about the visit of Lafayette to Monticello, the dinner given by the University for him, Jefferson's occasional rides in his carriage, her opinion of Charlottesville doctors, and Simon Bolivar's execution of Spanish prisoners
- Martha Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1825 September 1 (Box 1)
  remarks upon the press of constant visitors to Monticello on her energy and time, the poor health of her father and his problems with rheumatism, the visit of Lafayette and his promise to write Ellen from Washington, the delay in the sale of Edgehill, and attempts at a reconciliation between Thomas Mann Randolph and his son Jefferson Randolph
- Virginia Trist to Ellen Coolidge 1825 September 3 (Box 1)
  mentions the many visitors of summer, Nicholas Trist's visit to White Sulphur Springs for his health, her plan to secure a piano, and her brother Jefferson's disapproval of her plans
- Mary Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1825 September 11 (Box 1)
  discusses her heavy duties as a housekeeper at Monticello and the large number of guests, refers to Ellen's maid Sally [Coles] and her contentment as a nurse for little Miss Key, mentions an unpleasant encounter of the family with Charles Lewis Bankhead while he was intoxicated, and Mann Randolph's illness
- Martha Randolph to Joseph Coolidge, Jr. 1825 September 16 (Box 1)
  describes the flood of visitors due to the opening of the University, her attempts to screen the visitors to keep them from wearying her father, Thomas Jefferson's hope of visiting the University himself prevented by his poor health and the bad roads, and Jefferson's dose of 85 drops of laudanum each night for pain
- Martha Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1825 September 18 (Box 1)
  writes concerning the University "this neighborhood is becoming a place of general resort during the summer season, many parents who have sons at the University come to Charlottesville instead of going to the Springs," mentions that the [Rivanna?] River is too low for navigation that fall, and that Sally [Cole] was still working for Mrs. Key
- Mary Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1825 October 2 (Box 1)
  mentions the visit of Mrs. Madison and the members of the Board of Visitors at Monticello prior to their meeting at the University which Jefferson was finally able to visit by carriage
- Martha Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1825 October 13 (Box 1)
  expresses concern that Jefferson's health was damaged by his activity with the Board of Visitors of the previous week, describes the riot which occurred at the University involving Ayre, Wilson Cary, and Thompson who were expelled, the actions of George Long and Thomas Key who tried to withdraw from the faculty and offered their resignations, the Board's enactment of a rigid code of conduct for the students, General Cocke's advice to Wilson Cary's mother to place him in the country to read law, and lists the contents of Ellen's trunks subsequently lost at sea
- Virginia Trist to Ellen Coolidge 1825 October 16 (Box 1)
  mentions Cornelia's visit to Carysbrook, the terrible ordeal of Jefferson when a visiting plasterer, [J.H.I.] Browere, tried to make a mold of Jefferson's face but allowed the clay to harden too much causing much pain upon the mask's removal, and who also began working on a view of the University and some caricatures of several Monticello residents
- Mary Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1825 October 23 (Box 1)